Soviet Union Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Subject Files, Inclusive: 1939-2001, undated, Bulk: 1972-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Subject Files
Inclusive: 1939-2001, undated, Bulk: 1972-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
18
Keston Institute, 1969 -
8 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the history and persecution of the Ukrainian Catholic Church and Ukrainian Catholic clergy and believers in the Soviet Union.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the beginning of the post-World War II period until approximately 2007, Keston obtained materials documenting the religious and political climate and persecution of the Ukrainian Catholic Church, also called the Ukrainian Uniate Church and the Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church. Because of extreme persecution between 1949 and 1991, some referred to the body as “church of the catacombs.”
The Ukrainian Catholic Church, the largest of the Eastern Catholic Churches in full canonical communion with the Roman Catholic Church, recognizes the Pope of Rome as the supreme earthly head of the Church but follows Eastern traditions in liturgy, spirituality, sacred art, and organization. The Ukrainian Catholic Church traces its origin to Byzantine Christianity established in Kievan Rus’ by St. Vladimir in 988. In the Great Schism of 1054, the Eastern Churches remained with the Patriarchate of Constantinople. Their union with Rome was restored in 1596 at Brest-Litovsk. By that time, Kiev and most of the territory of modern Ukraine had become part of the predominately Catholic Grand Duchy of Lithuania. Although the Orthodox were opposed, the union guaranteed that the Eastern Church’s traditional rites would be sustained. In the late 1600’s, Kiev returned to Eastern Orthodoxy, but the western territories of modern Ukraine continued practicing Eastern-rite Catholicism.
Persecution of the Uniates began in the late 1700’s in Russian Empire-controlled territories. The tsarist government forced return to Orthodoxy, and the Ukrainian Catholic Church survived only in the province of Galicia which was controlled by the Austro-Hungarian Empire and later Poland. In 1939, Galicia became a part of the Soviet Union. After World War II, Soviet authorities suppressed the Church’s activities, which they viewed as Ukrainian nationalism and post-war Nazism. The Soviets pressured bishops to dissolve the Union of Brest-Litovsk and arrested, imprisoned, deported, or executed those who resisted. In March 1946, the Synod of Lvov ordered Ukrainian Catholics, particularly in western Ukraine and Transcarpathia, to become Russian Orthodox. Severe persecution resulted in the Ukrainian Catholic Church being almost eradicated. However, in 1989 the Church regained its legal status.
Scope and Content
Soviet Union Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Subject Files contain periodical clippings, trial transcripts, reports, scholarly journal articles, books, personal correspondence, personal notes of Michael Bordeaux, bibliographic cross-references, press releases, interrogation reports, and unofficial publications. Materials detail the circumstances that led to producing The Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine, and the collection contains nearly all of the periodical’s issues. The bulk of the materials date from 1972 to 1989 and emphasize persecution, church history, international relations, Vatican relations, incarceration of leaders, and Yosyp Terelya’s documentation of the persecution and history of the church. Notable individuals include, but are not limited to, Cardinal Iosif Slipyj, Yosyp Terelya, Metropolitan Klementy Sheptytsky, Myroslav Lubachivsky, Pope John Paul II, and Vasyl Kobryn.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Ukrainian Catholic Church materials in files organized by categories related to the political and religious context of the Church in the Soviet era. The original filing system has been preserved. Unprocessed materials received in no particular order are arranged thematically and chronologically.
Soviet Union Ukrainian Catholic (Uniate) Subject files are arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 18.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005.; Kobryn, Vasyl.; Lubachivsky, Myroslav.; Sheptytsky, Klementy.; Slipyi, Iosyf, 1892-1984.; Tereli︠a︡, Ĭosyp.
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Byzantine rite, Ukrainian -- Ukraine -- History -- 20th century.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Ukraine -- Church history -- 20th century.
Subjects
Communism and Christianity -- Ukraine -- History -- 20th century.; Persecution -- Ukraine -- History -- 20th century.
- General, 1939-1990; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains general information on the Ukrainian Catholic Church, especially as an underground church after 1946, and provides background on its context, culture, and persecution. Files are organized thematically and document not only the history but also the incarceration of key figures such as Cardinal Iosif Slipyj and attempts of later leaders such as Myroslav Lubachivsky to regain rights, alleviate persecution, and return to a relationship with the Vatican. The collection documents millennial celebrations and continued writings, activities, and incarceration of key leaders such as Yosyp Terelya and Vasyl Kobryn. A final section contains publications and information about events related to the Ukrainian Catholic Church in Canada.
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1939-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. General, 1988-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Bibliographic references, 1959-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Manuscripts and Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. History, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. History, 1971-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. History. Soviet Period, 1978-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Terelya, Yosyp (1 of 3), 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Terelya, Yosyp (2 of 3), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Terelya, Yosyp (3 of 3), 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church Administration, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - List of Ukrainian Catholic Churches, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Canon Law, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Synod of Bishops, 1977, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. 1946 Synod of Lvov (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. 1980 Synod, 1959, 1980 - 1981, 1985 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. State. Law, 1978, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church - State Relations, 1977, 1979-1980, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Legislation, 1987 - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Re-opening (Opening) of Ukrainian Catholic Churches, 1974, 1989, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Registration of Ukrainian Catholic Churches, 1977, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against the Ukrainian Catholic Church, 1976-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against the Ukrainian Catholic Church. Atheist Propaganda, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Harassment of Ukrainian Catholic Believers, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Physical Assault, Murder of Ukrainian Catholic Believers, 1977, 1980, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Disruption of Meetings (Services) of Ukrainian Catholic Believers, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Believers Fines, 1976, 1981, 1984, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Believers Trials, 1977, 1985, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Arrests. Imprisonment, 1972-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - State Interference in Ukrainian Catholic Church Affairs, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Refusal of Registration, Closure of Ukrainian Catholic Churches, 1986-1987, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Interference in Parish Level Administration of the (Folder 40)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Infiltration of the Ukrainian Catholic Church, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - State Expropriation, Demolition, or Desecration of Ukrainian Catholic Church Buildings, 1979, 1983, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Discrimination in Ukrainian Catholic Believers’ Employment, 1976, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Believers in Psychiatric Institutions, 1966, 1976-1981, 1987, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Attacks on the Ukrainian Catholic Church in Media, 1975, 1976, 1978-1980, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Believers. House Searches. Confiscation of Property, 1976, 1982, 1987, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church Life, 1980, 1981, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church Festivals and Anniversaries, 1978-1979, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Millennium of Baptism of Rus', 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Millennium Celebration in the Ukraine, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Canonization and Beautification, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Pilgrimages. Holy Places. Relics. Icons, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Pilgrimages. Holy Places. Relics. Icons. The Appearance of Virgin Mary at Grushev, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Parish Life, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Revival. Charismatic Renewal, 1983, 1987, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Monasticism, 1986, 1989, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Philanthropy, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Clergy. Priesthood, 1979, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Hierarchy, 1979-1980, 1982, 1985, 1987, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy, 1978, 1980, 1988, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Budzinsky, Grigory (Fr.), 1984, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Gorgula, Anatol Omelian (Fr.), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Havryliv, Mykhailo (Fr.), 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Lubachivsky, Myroslav (Cardinal) (1 of 2), 1980-1994, 2000, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Lubachivsky, Myroslav (Cardinal) (2 of 2), 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Sheptytsky, Andrey (Metropolitan), 1952, 1978, 1982, 1984, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Slipyj, Josyf (Cardinal) (1 of 2), 1963, 1972, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Slipyj, Josyf (Cardinal) (2 of 2), 1981-1992, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Sterniuk, Volodymyr (Archbishop), 1987, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Vynnytsky, Mykhaylo (Fr.), 1977, 1980, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Zeleniuk, Petro (Fr.), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Clergy. Chira, Alexander (Bishop), 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church Clergy. Living and Working Conditions, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church International Relations, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Western Reactions. Protests. Appeals (1 of 2), 1976-1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Western Reactions. Protests. Appeals (2 of 2), 1974-1987 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Contacts with International Organizations, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1988, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Activities Disapproved by the State, 1977-1984 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Public Demonstrations. Protests, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Defense of Believers' Rights. Litigation, 1983, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Defection. Emigration on Religious Grounds, 1982, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Defection. Emigration on Religious Grounds. Emigration of Fr. Myron Zhurakovsky, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Contacts with Foreigners, Émigrés, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Samizdat Monographs, Anthologies, Periodicals, etc., 1977, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Theology. Education. Morality. Philosophy, 1976, 1990, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Philosophy of Unity, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Statistics, 1976, 1977, 1988, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. United Kingdom, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. Vatican, 1979-1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. U.S. and Canada, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with Other Denominations, 1976, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with the Church of Norway, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with the Orthodox Church, 1979-1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Relations with the Roman Catholic Church, 1979, 1981-1983, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Contacts with Vatican, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Ecumenical Contacts. Gorbachev and Pope 1989 Summit in Rome (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Religion and National Identity (1 of 2), 1977-1980, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Religion and National Identity (2 of 2), 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church’s Involvement in Secular Affairs, Politics, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Literature, 1949, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Women, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Children, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church. Visual Materials, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - The Ukrainian Weekly, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Beacon, Ukrainian Rite Bimonthly, publication by the Order of Saint Basil the Great in Canada, 1978-1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Samizdat, 1984-1987; 2
  The series contains the samizdat publication The Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine written by Yosyp Terelya, often from prison, along with his prison correspondence which caused Pope John Paul II to become aware of the situation. The Holy See’s attention led to widespread foreign interest in the plight of Catholic believers in Ukraine in the 1980’s, especially in other predominately Catholic countries such as Italy and France and among Ukrainian Catholics abroad. Issues 1-9, 16-18, 22, 23, and two special editions of The Chronicle are included in their entirety.
  - Ukrainian Catholic Church-State Relations, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices Against Ukrainian Catholic Church Members. Trials. Misuse of Psychiatry, 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers Trials. Kobryn, Vasyl, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Imprisonment, State Interference in the Affairs of Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Terelya, Havryliv, Romanets, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Gorinya, Mikhailo, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Havryliv, Mykhailo, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Terelya's Open Letter to Yuri Andropov, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Individual Ukrainian Catholic Believers. Barladyanu, Vasyl, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. General, 1984-87 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issues 1-3, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issues 4-6, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issues 7-9, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Special Issue, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issues 16 and 18, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issue 22, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. Issue 23, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Chronicle of the Catholic Church in Ukraine. History, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Anonymous Manuscript in Ukrainian "Worthy Son of the Lithuanian People", undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Anonymous Manuscript in Ukrainian "Incomparable Christ", 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous Poem in Ukrainian "Memories of a Nurse", undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Anonymous Report on Millennium of Baptism of Rus' Celebration in Zarvanytsia, Ukraine, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)